在我们历史的最初
In the dawn of our history,
罗马的男人虽然孔武有力
we men of Rome were strong and fierce
却是粗野孤独的生物
but also uncouth and solitary creatures.
只有当我们娶妻成家之后
It was only when we acquired wives
我们才开始踏上成就伟大人格之路
that our rise to greatness truly began.
是罗马的女人们
It is the women of Rome
用她们无可动摇的道德
with their steely virtue and chaste morals
和高尚的节操征服了世界
who have conquered the world.
是她们的贞洁之光
It is by their virtuous light
照耀着我们男人踏过荆棘遍布的光荣之路
that we men have trod the perilous paths of glory.
是罗马的女人们
It is the women of Rome
在男人们征服迦太基时
who guarded hearth and home
保卫了他们的家园
while we men burnt Carthage.
是罗马的女人们
It is the women of Rome,
如同哺育罗穆卢斯和瑞摩斯的那头母狼一样
like the she-wolf that suckled Romulus and Remus,
养育了这个国家里睿智的政治家
who have raised a nation of wise statesmen
和战无不胜的勇士们
and invincible warriors.
我代表男人们
And on behalf of we men,
谨在此感谢你们所有人
I take this moment to thank you all.
一旦时机成熟
When the time is right,
我会让你们女人们
I shall make sure that you women
因你们的高尚道德而受到奖励
are rewarded for your virtue.
将来我会颁布法令
In the future, I shall enact laws
鼓励生育和圣洁的婚姻
that reward fertility and sanctity in marriage.
我会颁布法令
I shall enact laws
严惩通奸者
that severely punish adultery,
淫乱者
promiscuity
以及诸如此类的丑行
and vice of all kinds.
很不错 我会记住这一点的
That's very good. I shall remember that one.
恕我失陪
If you'll excuse me.
你觉得怎么样？
What did you think?
你的演讲？强劲有力
Your speech? Oh, strong stuff.
十分有趣 她们竟全盘接受了
Very amusing. They bought it wholesale.
我会说到做到
I mean every word.
是的 我知道你会的
Yes, I really think you do.
就我个人来说 我怀疑罗马过去的那些女人们
Myself, I suspect the women of old Rome
全是一帮婊子和泼妇
were a parcel of whores and termagants.
仁者见仁 智者见智
We shall agree to differ.
那就是我跟你说的年轻女人
There's the young piece I was telling you about.
算得上是个体面人家
She's very presentable.
照你的要求 完美的家世
As ordered. Impeccable family,
年轻 身体健康 能够生养
young, healthy, proven fertility.
- 生了几个孩子？- 就一个
- How many children? - Just the one.
一个儿子 泰彼琉斯
A son, Tiberius.
给我引见一下
Introduce me.
恺撒 容我为你介绍一下
Caesar, may I present
这位是阿菲迪娅 这是她女儿莉维娅
Alfidia and her daughter Livia?
不胜荣幸
Honored.
告诉我 你愿意嫁给我吗？
Tell me, how would you like to be married to me?
我…乐意之至
I would like that...
如果我丈夫不反对的话
if my husband does not object.
- 他叫什么名字？- 克劳迪亚斯·尼禄
- What is his name? - Claudius Nero.
我了解这家人 他们都是善良的爱国者
I know the family. They're good, patriotic people.
- 他们不会拒绝离婚的 - 我肯定他们不会拒绝 阁下
- They will not say no to a divorce. - I'm sure not, sir.
好极了
Excellent.
这事就交给你了
See to the details.
她会有不错的表现
She'll do nicely.
现在来谈点别的事 在我重新回到女人堆里之前
Now that other business before I dive back into this female swamp.
希律王的黄金等涨潮时 就会驶入奥斯提亚港
Herod's gold is offshore at Ostia waiting on the high tide.
我一直有和安东尼的手下伯斯卡联络 讨论运送的细节
I've been liaising with Antony's man, Posca, on the details of delivery.
我们考虑让艾文台的帮会来押运
We wanted to use the Aventine collegium for transportation,
如果你同意的话
if you are agreeable.
这主意不错 他们的人…
It's a good idea.
跟我 马克·安东尼是一条战线的 这样很好
They have men allied both to myself and to Mark Antony. That's good.
切勿走漏风声 绝对不能和我扯上关系
Make sure the entire business is invisible. I want complete deniability.
如果贿赂的事曝光
If the bribe comes to light,
只能怪到安东尼一个人头上
it must be Antony's fault alone.
爸爸 等我们到了耶路撒冷
Papa, when we get to Jerusalem,
里维埃叔叔会在那儿吗？
will Uncle Levi be there?
也许会 也许不会
Maybe. Maybe not.
还记得我们第一次相遇吗？
Remember when we first met?
- 就在你表亲的家 - 是的
- Your cousin's house. - Yes.
我看见了你 我就想
I saw you and I thought,
他 他就是我要找的好男人
"There. There is a good man for me.
虽然穿得不怎么样 不过是个好男人
"Maybe not such a nice dresser as I would like, but a good man."
过了这些年
It's been many years now,
你证明了我没看走眼
and you have never proved me wrong.
爸爸 我们还没到么？
Papa, are we there yet?
真漂亮啊 我能买下这个吗？
It's gorgeous. I can have it?
你想要什么都行 亲爱的
Anything you like, my love.
我的小糖糖
My little caramel.
你干吗不…
Why don't you...
进里边看看
go inside and see...
有没有什么你想要的
if there's anything else you like?
你对我真好
How good you are to me.
去吧
Off you go.
慢慢选
Take your time.
你就不能选不那么招摇的交通工具么？
You might have chosen a less conspicuous conveyance.
这是我第三好的轿子 你这么不起眼…被看见也无所谓
This is my third-best litter. You are nondescript enough for both of us.
那批 那批犹太货到了没有？
Has the... has the Judean shipment arrived yet?
你不用担心他们 我们说的话…他俩一句也听不懂？
You needn't worry about them. They don't understand a word we say.
不是吗 我亲爱的
Do you, my darlings?
下人们懂的东西比你想象的多
The lower orders understand more than you think.
说真的 你还真是可笑
Really, you are too absurd.
我们是在偷主子们的钱
We are stealing from our own chiefs.
如此谨慎并不可笑
No precaution we take is too absurd.
我可不认为这是偷 只不过为我们的贡献抽点佣金罢了
I wouldn't call it stealing. It is a commission for services rendered.
- 他们根本不会注意到这点亏空 - 别犯傻了
- They won't even notice the shortfall. - Don't fool yourself!
我们就是贼
We are thieves.
如果安东尼或屋大维发现了
If Antony or Octavian discover it,
我俩都要掉脑袋
we shall both die!
他们不会发现的
They won't discover it.
我们何时何地去抽取那佣金？
Where and when shall we extract our share?
艾文台的人会在晚上把东西… 送到土星的神庙去
The Aventine men will make delivery to the Temple of Saturn by night.
直到天亮 黄金就由你我俩守着
You and I will be alone with the gold until day.
带你最可靠的奴隶来
Bring slaves you trust.
- 哦 你好啊 米西纳斯 - 裘卡丝塔.
- Oh, hello, Maecenas. - Jocasta.
你干嘛坐这样 俗气的轿子里晃悠？
Why on earth do you travel in such a garish litter?
我差点以为我丈夫 被某个女演员勾搭上了呢
I thought sure my husband was intriguing with an actress
或是某个放浪的女人
or some such trollop.
真有趣
How amusing.
我们要去哪儿？
So where are we going?
黄金明天就运到奥斯提亚 阿格希码头
The gold will be in Ostia tomorrow, Argosy docks.
船名是"特赖登之王冠" [希腊神话中人身鱼尾的海神]
The ship's name, Triton's Crown.
我们就在那儿接手
We take it from there.
走陆路还是水路？
By river or road?
我听说屋大维和安东尼的人 会把黄金从水路运走
I'm told Octavian and Antony's men will take it by river.
所以我们走陆路…
So we'll take it by road,
避免沉船危险
avoid any leaks their end.
聪明
Clever.
不允许…
No one,
不许任何人打探货物内容
no one must know what the shipment contains.
一定要严守秘密
Secrecy is essential.
我叫拉斯卡和他的人去 他们比较可靠
I'll use Rasca and his boys. They're reliable.
- 他们从不乱打听 - 很好
- They don't ask questions. - Good.
但是波罗会接下这任务 不是你
But Pullo's gonna handle this, not you.
可一直都是我经手屋大维的事啊
I always handle Ostian business.
这次不一样
This is different.
你不相信我 是吗？
You don't trust me, is it?
我相信你 屋大维和安东尼 他们只认识波罗
I trust you. Octavian and Antony, they both know Pullo.
他们信任他
They trust him.
万一出了什么事 也不会怪罪到我们头上
Anything should go wrong, it won't come back at us.
没关系 我清楚得很
It's all right. I understand.
我不就是窝囊老三么
Third fucking man.
你的茶 女主人
Your tea, Domina.
救命 救命
Help! Help!
救命啊 谁来帮帮忙
Help! Help, somebody!
救命啊
Help!
叫医生来 叫医生来 艾瑞纳出事了
Get a doctor! Get a doctor! It's Eirene!
到处都是血 到处都是血
There's blood. There's blood!
她会治好你的 没问题的
She'll put you right. No trouble.
我不这么想
I don't think.
她会的
She will.
拜托 不要火葬
Please, no burning.
在我的国家 都是土葬的
In my country we are buried.
别说这种话
Don't talk like that.
不要火葬
No burning.
把我装进黑色的裹尸布
Put me in a black shroud...
葬在旷野上
and bury me in an open field.
不能有树
No trees. No trees.
你不会死的
You are not dying.
- 答应我 - 我什么也不答应 你不会死的
- Promise me. - I'll not promise anything. You are not dying.
答应我
Promise me.
等你头发都白了
When you're old and gray,
我答应我会给你土葬
I promise I'll bury you.
如果到时我先走一步的话 你可能都已经再嫁了
If I'm still around. You'll be onto your second husband by then.
孩子
The baby...
是儿子还是女儿？
Was it a boy or a girl?
儿子
A boy.
把他和我葬在一起
Bury him with me.
别伤心了
Don't be sad.
你让我也想哭了
You make me cry.
认识这女人
You gods that might know this woman
把她视为同族的神啊
as one of your own,
请听我说
please listen to me.
我们这里叫她艾瑞纳
We here call her Eirene,
在她的故乡 她被叫做爱妲拉
but she was called Adela where she came from,
就在莱茵河的那一边
somewhere beyond the Rhine,
虽不清楚具体地址
not sure exactly where.
她会告诉你们的
Anyway, you'll know her.
她是个好女人
She was a good woman.
她总是说您的好话
She always spoke very highly of you.
请务必要照顾她
So please look after her
还有我们的孩子
and our boy.
我的名字是泰特斯·波罗
My name is Titus Pullo,
曾经服役于第13军团
ex-13th Legion,
她的丈夫
her husband.
她在世的时候 我没有尽到应有的责任
Wasn't always as good to her as I should have been.
我无偿献上我的生命
I give my life to you to use as you like,
只求让她从此得到快乐
if you'll see that she's happy now.
是马修斯 阁下 出事了
It's Mascius, sir. There's trouble.
带路
Go on.
别乱动 马修斯 别动
Be still, Mascius. Be still.
小心点 你这混蛋 这又不是杀鸡
Careful, you bastard. I'm not poultry.
- 出了什么事？- 有埋伏…
- What happened? - Ambush...
还没到奥斯提亚门前就遇袭了
Just before we got to the Ostian Gate.
除了我跟他 全都死了
All but me and him are dead.
- 金子呢 - 没了
- The gold. - It's gone.
认得出是谁偷袭的？
Do you have any idea who it was attacked you?
认不出 但是他们身手不错
No. They were good, though.
没给我们任何机会
They didn't give us a chance.
兄弟
And brother,
他们是冲我们来的
they were waiting for us.
好了
All right.
叫所有人来 告诉他们翻遍整个城市
Call on every man. Tell them to cover the city.
用钱买 拷打逼问 如果必要 杀几个人
Pay coin, give torture, kill if necessary.
找出是谁干的
Find out who did this.
你 去陪着波罗 他要什么就给他什么
You, sit with Pullo. Make sure he has everything he needs.
我已经派人到全城搜查
I've men out all over the city looking into it.
我们很快就能找出是谁干的 出这么大事 肯定会有风声
We'll find out who's responsible soon. You can't keep a thing like this quiet.
对于一个害得主人损失惨重的人来说 你还真不害臊
For a man who has lost his masters a fortune, you show little shame.
我已经做了所有的预防措施 我派出了最好的人
I took all proper precaution. I used my best men.
你派泰特斯·波罗去了？
You used Titus Pullo?
没有
No.
为什么？他才是你最好的手下
Why? He is your best man.
他老婆昨天难产死了 所以我叫了别的人去
His wife died in childbirth yesterday, so I used another man.
我明白 我明白
I see. I see.
这个嘛
Well...
还真是推得干净
Very convenient.
- 我不懂你什么意思 - 屋大维信任的人…
- I do not take your meaning. - The one man we know Octavian can trust
被临时被个无名小卒替换了
is replaced at the last minute by who knows who?
这方法还真好用
That's very convenient.
你是指责我在背后捣鬼？
Are you accusing me of being involved in this?
我同样也可以怪到你身上
I could just as easily accuse you.
- 或者是莱彼德斯 - 胡说八道
- Or Lepidus. - That's ridiculous.
不需要相互指责
No one is accusing anyone.
帮里会不会有内奸？
Could it be that one of your own men betrayed you?
什么都有可能 可我不信有这个可能
Anything is possible, but I doubt it.
为什么？
Why?
他们都怕我
They are scared of me.
- 那么是谁？- 问得好
- Then who? - Good question.
如果不是我的人 会是谁？
If not one of my men, then who?
别把矛头指向别人
Do not lay the blame elsewhere.
是你负责看管我们的财物
You had custody of our property.
任何损失都是你的责任
Its loss is your responsibility.
我明白 我会找到你们的钱 然后带回来
I understand. I will find your property and bring it back.
你最好说到做到
Be sure that you do.
你很清楚失败的后果
You know the consequences of failure.
我来告诉你们是谁干的
I'll tell you who it was.
高卢人
Gauls.
要我赌多少钱都行 一定是高卢人
I'll wager any amount of money it was Gauls.
他们跟兔子一样会生
They breed like rabbits, you know.
没有劳动谋生的概念
No notion of working for a living.
大部分都是盗贼
Thieves, the lot of them.
我知道是你干的
I know it was you.
我知道
I know.
你跟安东尼一起阴我
You and Antony double-crossed me.
- 我向你保证… - 不 不 不
- I assure you... - No, no, no.
我向你保证
I assure you,
你们两个会付出代价的
you'll both pay.
乌瑞纳斯老兄 欢迎欢迎 坐吧
Brother Vorenus. Welcome, sit.
喝上几杯 给老大腾个位子 小子们
Have some wine. Make a way for the captain, boys.
一个人来的？
Come alone?
你在庆祝什么东西啊 嗯？
You celebrating something?
不 我们只不过是群乐天派
No, we're just happy sort of people.
我负责的一些财物昨天晚上 在奥斯提亚那边被抢
Property in my charge was stolen on the Ostia Way last night.
- 哦 天哪 什么财物？- 国家财产
- Oh, dear. What sort of property? - Belonging to the state.
喔 那可不妙啊 很不高兴吧 我猜都是些好货色
That's not good. Peeved, I'll bet, the quality.
- 确实是 - 不是我们干的吧 是吗？
- They are. - Wasn't us, was it?
国家财产？我们？
With state property? Us?
不可能 我们哪儿敢
No, we wouldn't dare.
不 不是我们干的
No, wasn't us.
我没说是你们呢
I didn't say it was.
那你是来话家常的？
Just a social visit, then?
如果你碰巧听到 这事儿是谁犯的
If you happen to hear who it was did this,
- 你肯定会通知我吧 - 当然
- I'm sure you'll tell me. - Certainly.
绝不能让人劫了老大 那可太丢脸了 会让我们所有人难堪的
Can't have people robbing a fellow captain. It's humiliating. It makes us all look bad.
这个国家财物 到底是什么？
What was it exactly, this state property?
这跟你无关
That doesn't matter.
不知道该找什么 我们就帮不上忙了
Can't help if we don't know what we're looking for.
你是对的
You're right.
别在意 你已经帮了大忙了
Never mind. You've helped more than enough already.
谢谢你 莫密欧 我们很快就会再见面的
Thank you, Memmio. I will see you again soon.
乐意之至
Always a pleasure.
我的建议是 查查你自己的人
My advice... look to your own people.
这种事情经常都是身边的人干的
This kind of affair is nearly always someone close.
和库塔还有艾萨伯说一声 以及其它的首领 我今天就要见他们
Go tell Cotta, Acerbo, and the other captains I need to see them today.
- 艾萨伯也叫？- 你听到我说的了
- Acerbo? - You heard me.
- 我希望你能更严肃地看待这件事 - 这种事常有
- I wish you took this seriously. - These things happen.
- 这可是一大笔钱 - 我们还会从别的地方弄到更多的钱
- It's a great deal of money. - More money will come.
外面有上千个腰包鼓鼓的王公 或总督之类的等着称王
A thousand rich dukes and satraps want to be kings.
劫得是"你"的财物 不是什么杂货店老板
But you were robbed as if you were some petty grocer.
告诉我 为什么你会觉得 这件事这么难以接受？
Tell me, why do you take such personal offense at this?
这是对你个人极大的侮辱
It is a gross personal insult to you.
总会有人在某处侮辱我 这就是当名人的代价
Someone is always insulting me. It's the price of fame.
马克·安东尼可不是无名之辈 他是你的同僚 你姐夫
Mark Antony is your colleague and brother-in-law.
如果你能证明这件事 安东尼也有份 不妨说出来
If you have proof that Mark Antony is responsible, tell me.
还有谁知道这船货？还能是谁？
Who else knew of the shipment?
- 莱彼德斯吗？- 完全有可能 很可能这只是个意外
- Lepidus? - Very possibly. It's likely it was an accident.
不是意外 就是安东尼干的
There are no accidents. It was Antony.
自从我们讲和后 他一直待我即公正又坦诚
Since we reconciled, he has been just and honest.
我不会冒险损害我们的联盟 就因为你不喜欢那个人
I won't jeopardize our alliance because you dislike him.
我知道的事实是 他对你既不公正也不坦诚
I know for a fact he's been neither just nor honest with you.
他一直在耍你
He's been making a fool of you.
你什么意思？
What do you mean?
原谅我 我以为不告诉你最好 你跟他的联盟为了共和国好
Forgive me, I thought it best not to tell you. Your alliance, the wellbeing of the republic...
说啊
Speak!
安东尼和你姐姐的婚礼只是个幌子
Antony's marriage to your sister is a sham.
他还同以前一样跟你妈上床
He's been bedding your mother as before.
这不可能 安东尼不敢这么侮辱我 除此之外 奥克塔维娅…
That's impossible. Antony would not dare disrespect me like that, and Octavia...
奥克塔维娅一定会告诉我的
Octavia would have told me.
她有她自己保持沉默的理由
She has her own reasons for keeping silent.
女主人 你儿子叫你去…
Domina, your son summons you
参加今天的晚宴
to dinner this evening.
告诉他不必了 我要去剧院
Tell him no. I am going to the theater.
他说这很重要 必须出席
He says it's important. Attendance is compulsory.
他越来越像个官僚了
He's getting more and more officious.
还有谁去？
Who else is coming?
全是家庭成员
Just family.
谢谢你们所有人这么快就赶来了
Thank you all for coming so promptly.
我有很要紧的事要跟你们商量
I have urgent business to discuss.
- 就这个？- 耐心点 库塔
- With these? - Patience, Cotta.
- 我认为你会对我说的事很感兴趣 - 橄榄油半价 是吗？
- You'll like what I have to say. - Giving half price on olive oil?
不 我想在谷物生意上多捞一笔
No. Rather, I was thinking of getting deeper into the grain trade.
跟乌瑞纳斯之间已经走到头了
Things with brother Vorenus are coming to a head.
我认为是时候制止他的傲慢无礼了
I'm thinking it's time to put an end to his arrogance.
原来真是你
So it was you.
- 你劫了他的黄金 - 什么黄金？
- You took his gold. - What gold is that?
街上每个乞丐都在谈论的黄金 原来是你
The gold every beggar in the city is talking about. It was you.
- 可能是 我没说是我 - 但是可能是
- Might have been. I don't say that it was - But it might have been.
- 你想独吞？- 独吞什么？
- And you kept it from me? - Kept what from you?
- 别跟我开玩笑 - 你拿了他的黄金？
- Don't joke with me. - You took his gold?
乌瑞纳斯认为是我干的
Vorenus thinks I did.
他想把你枭首示众 所以你害怕了
So he's after your head on a stick and you're scared.
- 跟我们有什么关系？- 没人可以单独接管艾文台的生意
- What's that to us? - No one can handle the Aventine on their own.
可要是我们所有人合作 就跟亲兄弟一样
But if all of us were to cooperate, like the brothers we are, different story.
- 那就完全不同了 - 我们会打垮他们
- Story! - We'll crush them.
艾文台就归我们了 谷物生意也归我们了
The Aventine will be ours. The grain trade will be ours.
慢着 慢着 慢着
Wait, wait, wait, wait, wait.
我可没指望你们为了兄弟情谊来帮我
I don't expect you to help me out of brotherly love.
就这样 孩子们
That's it, boys.
这才是你们想要的 对吧？
That's what you want, isn't it?
来啊 捡起来
Yes! Pick it up!
看 那儿还有
Missed a bit there. Look.
这就是你们要的 再来点
That's what you want, a bit more!
来了 还有 还有
Here it comes. More! More!
很好 现在去捡啊
That's right! Now, pick it up.
对不起 我不说话 吓到你了
Forgive me. I unnerve you with my silence.
没有 大人
No, sir.
你的手真小
What small hands you have.
- 很干燥 - 谢谢
- So dry. - Thank you.
告诉我 你丈夫打过你吗？
Tell me, does your husband ever beat you?
没有 大人
No, sir.
但愿我从没有做过让他生气的事
I hope I have never given him reason to do so.
- 那么你父亲呢？- 也没有 大人
- Your father, perhaps? - No, sir.
你很守妇德 很好 非常好
A virtuous woman. Good. That is good.
但你要知道 我们结婚后 我有时会打你
You should know that when we are married, I shall, on occasion, beat you,
用手打 或用鞭子抽
with my hand or a light whip.
我打你的时候 不要认为是你做错了什么
When I do, do not think you have offended me.
我打你会让我产生性快感
I do it because it gives me sexual pleasure.
所以记得不要难过
You must remember that and not be upset.
好的 大人
Yes, sir.
我想我们会相处的很好
I think we shall get along very well.
人到齐了
They're all here.
可以开始了吧
About time.
卢西尔斯·乌瑞纳斯那儿有消息吗？
Any news from Lucius Vorenus?
- 没有 - 奇怪
- No. - Strange.
我们要耐心 乌瑞纳斯向来说话算数
We must be patient. Vorenus always does what he says he'll do.
- 很高兴你这样想 - 这个小美人是谁？
- I am glad you think so. - And who is this sweet creature?
这是莉薇娅 李维乌斯·杜路苏斯·克劳迪乌斯的女儿
This is Livia, daughter of Livius Drusus Claudianus.
- 我要娶她 - 太好了 欢迎加入这个大家庭
- I'm going to marry her. - How nice. Welcome to the family.
谢谢 很高兴认识您
Thank you. I am glad to make your acquaintance.
这一定是我的姐姐奥克塔维娅
And this must be my sister Octavia.
真是天生丽质
Such a lovely complexion she has.
你瞒得真好
What a furtive person you are.
我一点都没看出来你想结婚
I had no inkling you were looking to marry.
我带她来是希望
I wanted her to be here
她能清楚的知道并了解 成为这个家的一份子代表了什么
so she would properly understand what it means to be a part of this family.
就是高级奴隶
It's a species of benign slavery.
奴隶？是吗？
Slavery, is it?
你以为你是斯巴达克斯吗？[古罗马奴隶起义领袖]
Well, you fancy yourself a Spartacus then, do you?
- 我不懂你在说什么 - 我是一家之主
- I don't follow. - I am master of this family,
你却要跟我造反
and you have rebelled against me.
- 我倒希望有这胆子 - 你已经胆大包天了 我真是惊讶
- I wish I had such courage. - You are courageous enough. I was surprised.
对于母亲的各种堕落行为 我已经习以为常了
I knew Mother had the stomach for any kind of depravity,
但是你 我太吃惊了
but you, I was surprised.
对于我一直以来对你的仁爱 你的回报就是背叛
I have shown you nothing but love and you repay me with treachery.
我的同僚 别忘了
Remember, colleague,
- 你在和我的妻子说话 - 你名义上的妻子
- you are talking to my wife. - Your wife in name only.
给你尽妻子义务的 还是我母亲 不是吗？
It is still Mother that performs the wifely function, is it not?
同时奥克塔维娅 还和我的好朋友阿格里帕有染
While Octavia does the same for my good friend Agrippa.
你们倒是给大伙都行了方便了
That's very convenient for all involved.
- 你到底什么意思？- 你否认吗？
- What are you getting at? - Do you deny it?
- 你没资格质问我 - 你否认吗？
- I'll not be interrogated by you! - Do you deny it?
去操你的小姑娘吧 少管我的事
Fuck your little girl and leave my business to me!
- 你否认吗？- 确实如此
- Do you deny it? - It's true.
我不否认
I'll not deny it.
我爱你姐姐
I love your sister.
我们幽会已经有段时间了
We have been meeting in secret for some time now.
但我不能替安东尼回答
But I cannot answer for Antony.
谢谢 阿格里帕 谢谢你的诚实
Thank you. Thank you for being honest with me.
那怎么样？是真的又怎么样？你想怎么着？
So what? What if it is true? What are you gonna do about it?
你拿我没有办法
There is nothing you can do about it.
我要把我的女人都带回去
I shall send my women to their house,
她们将被隔离看管
where they shall remain in seclusion under guard
- 没有我的命令不准放行 - 这我办不到
- until I say so. - I'll do no such thing!
闭嘴
Silence.
而你 你得离开罗马
You, you shall leave this city.
- 离开罗马？- 你要去东部属于你的省份
- Leave this city? - You shall go east to your provinces
- 不许再回来 - 不然怎么样 小家伙？
- and you shall not come back. - Or else what, boy?
你要离开罗马 否则我就宣布同盟条约失效
Leave this city, or I declare our alliance is broken.
我要告诉众人这丑闻
I shall have this sad story told in the Forum.
把它传遍意大利的所有城市
I will have it posted in every city in Italy.
你知道 人民对于妻子的态度 可没有你那么开放
And you know, the people are not so liberal with their wives as you are.
他们会说你被扣上了绿帽子
They will say you wear cuckold's horns.
会说你妻子为了我手下 出身低贱的贫民背叛了你
They will say your wife betrayed you with a lowborn pleb on my staff.
你会成为笑柄
You will be a figure of fun.
老百姓当街笑话你
The proles will laugh at you in the street.
你的士兵背地里嘲笑你
Your soldiers will mock you behind your back.
来吧 揍我啊
Go on. Strike me.
看看会怎么样
See what happens.
对了 安东尼
Oh, and Antony,
找到金子后 你肯定会通知我的对吧？
if you find that gold, you'll be sure to tell me, won't you?
- 你这样会让你姐姐蒙羞 - 让她蒙羞的是她自己
- You would disgrace your own sister? - She has disgraced herself.
很高兴认识你
It was nice to meet you.
自己保重
Take care.
你嫁了一个怪物
You're marrying a monster.
带她们回家 带上守卫
Take them home. Take guards with you.
确保她们安全到家
Make sure they get home... safely.
是你告诉他的吧？
It was you who told him, wasn't it?
我早就看出你是什么货色了
I always knew you were a weasel.
夫人 我很希望向你表达歉意 但是这是我的职责所在
I wish I could apologize, madam, but it was my duty.
你害了你的主人 现在他失去了所有的家人
You've done your master a terrible disservice. Now he has no family at all.
米西纳斯
Maecenas.
别怪他 他做了他认为对的事
Do not blame him. He did what he thought was right.
- 你就做不出来 - 我很抱歉
- I do not think you can say the same. - For which I apologize.
别让奥克塔维娅因为我犯的错而受罪
But do not let Octavia suffer for my sins.
是我的错
The fault is mine.
是我先勾引她的
It was I seduced her.
你很有才华 阿格里帕
You have many talents, Agrippa.
但是你不懂怎么勾引人
Seduction is not one of them.
你不该对她这么残忍
She does not deserve your cruelty.
- 她没有… - 我该说的已经说了
- She's not... - I've stated my intentions.
你不会被流放 我这里需要你
You will not be banished. I need you.
另外 你的突然消失 会引起流言蜚语
Besides, your sudden disappearance would suggest some sort of scandal.
我…谢谢你
I thank you.
你可以走了
You can go.
你该尝尝瓤馅鸟
Try one of the stuffed songbirds.
这是我厨子的拿手好菜
My cook does them particularly well.
他吃过吗？
Has he eaten?
水呢？
Water?
波罗
Pullo.
波罗 你两天没喝水了 你得喝点什么
Pullo, you've had no water in two days. You need to drink something.
我去看过马修斯 伤得不轻
Mascius looked in. Cut up nasty.
喝
Drink.
金子丢了 对吧？
Gold got stolen, did it?
除了马修斯和齐诺 其他人都死了
All but Mascius and Zeno are dead.
你别操心了
Don't you worry about it.
我会找回来的
I'll... I'll get it back.
莫密欧？
Memmio?
似乎是 我去找过他
Looks like. I went to see him.
很明显他脸上带着罪恶感
He had guilt written on his face very plain.
谁告的密？
Who told him?
他还好心的提醒我有内鬼
He as good as said it was one of my own people.
马修斯
Mascius.
- 他一直很不满意 - 而且他活着回来
- He's not been happy. - And he lived.
但他一直很忠诚
Still, he's always been loyal.
以前从没怀疑过他
Never had to doubt him before.
奸细不会让你看出来
No one's a traitor until they are.
波罗 你去哪儿？
Pullo, where are you going?
马修斯
Mascius.
我没事 波罗
All right, Pullo.
老大
Boss.
感觉怎么样？
How are you feeling?
还不坏 我很幸运
Not so bad. I was lucky.
确实很幸运
Very lucky.
还没有金币的消息？
No word yet?
放回去
Give it back!
- 放回去 - 孩子们 安静
- Give it! - Children, quiet.
我唯一能想到的就是或许…
The only thing I can think of is maybe...
或许是屋大维 或安东尼其中一个派人干的
Maybe one of Octavian or Antony's men set it all up.
不可能 他们以为我们走水路 他们不可能知道我们走陆路
Couldn't be. They thought we'd go by river. Didn't know we'd use the road.
没错
True.
莫密欧说我们该查查自己人
Memmio said that we should look to one of our own.
听着…
Listen...
兄弟
brother,
我们都命悬一线
our lives are on the line.
你必须负这个责任
You wanted the responsibility.
- 我们只要你的回答 - 除了你没有别人了
- We just want some answers. - It had to be you.
开玩笑 你认为我自己把自己砍成这样？
You're joking. You think I did this myself?
马修斯 整个计划只有我们三个人知道
Mascius, the only people who knew what the plan was was we three here.
他妈的老三
Third fucking man.
- 不是我 - 放回去
- It wasn't me. - Give it back!
给我 出去
Give me that. Get out of here.
不许再进来了
Don't come back in here.
说实话吧
Just tell the truth.
对不起 兄弟
I'm sorry, brother.
我们一起当兵将近20年 你们和我
Near on 20 years marching together, you boys and me.
- 说实话 - 实话？
- Tell the truth. - The truth?
实话就是我把你当兄弟看
The truth is I have known you as a brother.
实话就是在艾格威雅我救过你一命
The truth is I saved your life at Gergovia.
为此挨了一箭
Took an arrow for it.
箭头还在身体里
Arrow's still in there.
实话就是如果重来一次我还是会救你
The truth is I'd do it again, brother.
实话就是我除了是你的手下就什么也不是 还有什么好朋友
The truth is I've been nothing but a good soldier and a good fucking friend.
要杀要剐随你 兄弟
You do what you have to do, brother.
地狱见
See you in Hades.
- 金币在哪儿？- 波罗 卢西尔斯
- Where's the gold? - Pullo! Lucius!
- 什么？- 卢西尔斯
- What? - Lucius!
这个从哪儿来的？
Where did you get this?
父亲
Father.
父亲 住手
Father, stop it.
住手
Stop it!
住手 你在干什么 别翻了
Stop it! What are you doing? Stop it!
父亲 住手
Father! Stop it!
- 这些东西从哪儿来的？- 我买的
- Where'd you get these? - I bought them.
不要骗我
Don't you lie to me.
是我买的
I did.
是莫密欧的人给你的是不是？
One of Memmio's men gave them to you.
- 是不是？- 不是 我不懂你说什么
- Didn't he? - No, I don't know...
- 不许说谎 - 我没说谎
- Don't you lie to me. - I'm not lying.
回来 给我回来
You get back here. Get back here!
是你 对不对 是你
It was you, wasn't it? It was you. You went to Memmio.
是你告的密 你背叛了我
It was you who betrayed me.
你去卖身了是不是？你卖身给了莫密欧的人
You've been whoring yourself to one of Memmio's men.
你他妈卖身给了混蛋西莲公社
You've been whoring yourself to the whole damn Caelian.
才不是 他爱我
That's not true. He loves me.
他爱我 我也爱他
He loves me and I love him.
你怎么这么蠢？
How could you be so stupid?
他是利用你对付我
He was using you to get to me.
你什么都不懂
You know nothing about it.
他爱我
He loves me.
为了这样一个人渣的爱
And for love of this scum
你居然背叛你的亲身父亲？
you would betray your own father?
噢是啊 我背叛了你
Oh, yes! I betrayed you!
我再高兴不过了
And I was glad to do it.
为什么？
Why?
为什么？为什么？为什么这么做？
Why? Why? Why would you do that?
你杀了我母亲
You killed my mother.
你咒我们下地狱
You cursed us to Hades.
你让我被卖去当妓女
You made me a fucking whore.
你还有脸问为什么？
And you ask why?
因为我恨你
Because I hate you.
我恨你 我们都恨你
I hate you! We all hate you.
我希望你死
I wish you were dead.
动手啊
Go ahead.
过来杀我啊 好象你杀了妈妈一样
Try and kill me like you killed Mother.
我没有这么容易对付
I'll not go so easy.
- 我没有杀她 - 骗子
- I didn't kill her. - Liar.
- 我没有杀她 - 她不爱你 所以你就杀了她
- I didn't. - She didn't love you. You killed her for it.
闭嘴 你给我闭嘴
Shut your mouth. Shut your mouth.
- 她从来没有爱过你 - 给我闭嘴
- She never loved you. - You shut your mouth.
- 她从来没有爱过你 - 闭嘴 闭嘴
- She never loved you. - You shut... shut...
闭上你的嘴
Keep your mouth shut!
乌瑞纳斯
Vorenus.
三巨头之一伟大的马克·安东尼宣布
Our noble triumvirate announces the immediate departure
将立刻离开罗马
from the city of his honor Mark Antony.
他将接管亚历山大城
He will take up his seat in Alexandria
接任埃及的最高统治者
as supreme governor of Egypt
以及领导东部各行省
and the eastern provinces.
明天 在鲁福斯家
Tomorrow, at the house of Rufus,
举行奴隶拍卖会
an auction of excellent slaves,
不论是柔顺听话的处女 还是训练有素的希腊人
from pliant virgins to learned Greeks,
鲁福斯家的拍卖会应有尽有
Rufus has slaves for every budget.
给领袖马克·安东尼让路
Make way for the Triumvir Mark Antony.
伟大领袖屋大维·凯撒有令
Orders of his honor Triumvir Octavian Caesar,
任何人不得进入房子
none shall enter this house.
要动武吗？
Shall we use force?
不
No.
阿提娅
Atia!
让开 你们这些可鄙的虫子
Out of my way, you little insects.
夫人 很抱歉 没有命令我们不能让您出去
You cannot leave without permission.
阿提娅 冷静
Atia, calm.
别硬来
Leave it be.
我只说几句话
I just want to talk.
别逼我动粗 百夫长
Don't push me to violence, centurion.
只能说话
Just talk.
我明天动身
I'm leaving tomorrow.
很好
Very well.
再见
Goodbye, then.
时机一旦成熟
When the time comes,
我就派人来接你
I'll send for you.
什么时候？
When will that be?
谁知道呢？
Who can say?
我们要耐心
We must be patient.
答应我 答应我你一定会来接我
Promise me. Promise me you'll send for me.
以我的性命…起誓
On my life, I promise.
烧了
Burn it.
- 这份呢？- 我不知道
- And this? - I don't know.
烧了 拿去擦屁股 我不在乎
Burn it. Wipe your arse with it. I really don't care.
好啊 好啊
Well, well.
卢西尔斯·乌瑞纳斯
Lucius Vorenus.
找到我的金子了吗？
You found my gold yet?
- 我知道它们在哪儿 - 然后呢？
- I know where it is. - And?
泰特斯·波罗会夺回金币
Titus Pullo will retrieve it.
我…我已经从帮会退位了
I have resigned from the collegium.
- 退位？- 因为私事
- Resigned? - It's a personal matter.
我绝对相信…波罗不会让您失望
I have no doubt Pullo will not let you down.
我也曾肯定你不会让我失望 但是看看我们现在
I had no doubt that you would not let me down, but here we are.
我很抱歉
For that, I apologize.
我来是表示我仍愿为您效忠
I am come to offer you my services
去埃及 如果您带上我的话
in Egypt, if you will take me.
你的效忠？在埃及？
Your services? In Egypt?
我不能留在罗马 长官
I cannot stay in Rome, sir.
让我跟您去埃及吧
Let me go to Egypt with you.
请您准许
Please.
好吧
All right.
跟我一起去
Come with me.
我需要人手
I need good men.
你不会从此酗酒吧？
You'll not turn to drink, will you?
不会 长官
No, sir.
你们这种宿命论者常常这样
Well, you stoic types often do
一旦生活不如意的话
when disappointed in life.
欢迎加入
Welcome aboard.
谢谢 长官
Thank you, sir.
- 他怎么说？- 我们明天出航
- What did he say? - We sail tomorrow.
你不回去和孩子们告别吗？
You're not gonna come back and say goodbye?
不
No.
沃伦娜毕竟是你的孩子
Vorena's got your blood in her.
不轻易原谅人 但她还年轻…
Doesn't forgive easy. And she's young.
- 姑娘们 - 波罗 这样对我们最好
- Girls... - Pullo, it's best this way.
好好照顾他们好吗？
You'll take good care of them?
告诉他们…
Tell them...
我试过想做个好父亲
Tell them I tried.
诸神会看顾你 兄弟
Gods protect you, brother.
你也是 兄弟
And you, brother.
- 别摘了 - 为什么不？
- Don't do that. - Why not?
这些花很贵
I paid good money for those flowers.
再这样我们这儿最终会变成沙漠
You'll leave the place a desert if you carry on.
我没其他事可做
I've nothing better to do.
你干嘛不去厨房 也许那儿有让你开心的事
In the kitchen you might find something to amuse you.
去干什么？帮厨子剥洋葱皮？
What? Help the cook peel onions?
有比这更好的事
Better than that.
不过在我看来 也好不到哪儿去
Well, not much better, in my opinion.
你对男人的品味一向不高
You always did have lamentable taste in men.
去吧
Go on.
别让守卫看出来你在笑
And don't let the guards see you smile.
免得他们看出不对劲 去吧
They'll know something's amiss. Go on.
你到底怎么进来的？
How on earth did you get in?
屋大维的人连只老鼠都不会放过
Octavian's men don't let a mouse get by them.
你母亲很有办法
Your mother could outfox Ulysses.
如果她能让你进来 那她也许能帮我逃出去
Well, if she can get you inside, perhaps she can get me out.
我们可以一起走
We could run away together.
好主意 但是…
It's a nice thought but...
- 不可能 - 我们至少可以试一试
- ...it's not possible. - We could try, at least.
- 不 - 为什么不？我有一点钱
- No. - Why not? I have a little money.
我们可以去东部 他找不到我们的
We could go to the east. He couldn't reach us there.
和你 就算入地狱我也愿意
I would go with you to Hades,
甚至去不列颠 如果我们有权利远走高飞的话
to Britain, even, if I thought we had the right.
但我们没有
But we don't.
权利？
Right?
那他又有什么权利把我关在这儿？
What right has he to keep me captive?
- 他有什么权利… - 够了
- What right has he to... - Please.
请不要生气
Don't be angry.
不管是法律上还是道德上 他都有权利按照他的意愿处置我们
He has every legal and moral right to do with us as he wishes.
他原谅了我
He has forgiven me.
仍旧做我的朋友
And he remains my friend.
我不能不回报他的宽容 我不能再一次背叛他
I cannot repay his forgiveness by betraying him a second time.
那你来这儿干什么？
Well, why are you here, then?
来告别
I'm here to say goodbye.
你要去哪儿？
Where are you going?
我是说 我们还是能见面
I mean, we shall see each other again,
经常见面 我想
quite often, I expect.
但是我们的关系要恢复正常 我们要保持距离
But our relations will be formal and correct as they should be.
懦夫
Coward.
你是个可怜的懦夫
You're a miserable coward.
- 奥克塔维娅 - 别说了 我理解
- Octavia... - No. I understand.
你爱我弟弟 和他给你的权利
You love my brother and the power he gives you.
为什么要把这些浪费在一个女人身上？
Why throw that all away for a woman?
这样很蠢
It'd be very foolish.
再见
Goodbye.
顺便说一句
Oh, by the way,
我怀孕了
I'm having a baby.
谁是父亲？
Who is the father?
谁知道呢？
Who knows?
反正你们俩都不配 何必计较呢？
Neither man is worth a brass obol, so what matter?
走 走 走
Go, go, go!
快 关上门
Quickly, shut the door.
泰特斯·波罗
Titus Pullo.
谈判吧
A parley.
波罗兄弟 我和你没什么可吵的
Brother Pullo, I have no quarrel with you.
你是个讲道理的人 像我一样
You're a reasonable man like I am.
全是疯子乌瑞纳斯把我们逼上这步的
It's that madman Vorenus took us to this pass.
你和我没道理不能好好谈生意
No reason you and me can't do business.
13军团
13!
站好了 不许逃 胆小鬼
Stand firm! Don't run, you cowards!
[亚历山大城 埃及]
安东尼
Antony.
克莉奥佩特拉
Cleopatra.